Kate Upson Clark Papers, 1893-1935
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Kate Upson Clark papers
1893-1935
Clark, Kate Upson, 1851-1935
MS 34
2 boxes (.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Editor, Trustee, Wheaton College, Suffragist, Journalist, Poet. Papers include diaries; correspondence with family and friends, manuscripts, lectures, biographical material and memorabilia. Her unpublished manuscript of "The Affair of William Strickland & Co.," is an account of charges of "Abolitionist connivance" brought against her father, Edwin Upson.
Catherine (Kate) Pickens Upson was born in Alabama in 1851, to Edwin Upson and Priscilla Maxwell. She was raised in Charlemont, Massachusetts and graduated from Wheaton Female Seminary (now Wheaton College), Norton, Mass., in 1869. In 1874, she married Edward P. Clark, and they had three sons, Charles, John and George. She contributed articles and columns to periodicals including Godey's Magazine, Atlantic Monthly, Christian Herald, Harper's and various children's magazines. She was editor of the Springfield (Mass.) Republican, Good Cheer Magazine, and eventually the New York Evening Post. She published several books (mostly children's), short stories, and a novel.
After her husband's death in 1903, Kate Clark lectured extensively throughout U.S. on popular, cultural, literary, and political subjects including suffrage. She resided in New York City and was active in the suffrage and temperance movements, and founded the Brooklyn's Women's Republican Club. She taught courses on lecturing at Columbia University and was a trustee of Wheaton College from 1907 until her death in 1935.
[See also Clark Family Tree in reading room]
The Kate Upson Clark Papers include diaries, correspondence, published and unpublished writings (including notes, articles, lectures, and poems), biographical material and memorabilia. Correspondence from and to family, friends, and students includes intimate letters (1914-22) to her sister, Mary Upson Avery, covering personal, family, occupational, and financial matters, and including references to her activities as a Trustee of Wheaton College, persons of varying importance met through lecture engagements, and glimpses into the careers of her sons, Charles Upson and John Kirkland Clark. Her unpublished manuscript, "The Affair of William Strickland & Co.," is an account of charges of "Abolitionist connivance" brought by the booksellers' business in Mobile, Alabama in which her father Edwin Upson, a native of Connecticut, was an associate. Other writings include composition books (1862-67); diaries she kept as an adolescent and young woman (1862-68, 1888); and extensive notes on a European trip (1923-25).
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
The Kate Upson Clark Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by her son, Charles Upson Clark, circa 1950 and 1961.
Search Terms
Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Abolitionists--Indiana--Biography--Sources; Clark, Kate Upson, 1851-1935; Family--United States--History--19th century--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Journalists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women journalists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women editors--United States--Biography--Sources; Wheaton College (Norton, Mass.)--History--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional papers are housed in the Wheaton College Archives and Special Collections, Norton, Mass.
Contents List
  - Correspondence
    - Kate Upson Clark to family, 1914-15 (Box 1)
    - Kate Upson Clark to Mary (sister) and Oscar Avery, 1916-22 (Box 1)
    - Friends to Kate Upson Clark, 1919-26, undated (Box 1)
    - Edwin Markham to Kate Upson Clark, 1906 (Box 1)
    - Friends to Edward P. Clark (husband), 1874-89 (Box 1)
    - Friends and relatives to Mary P. Upson, 1899, undated (Box 1)
    - Students to Mary P. Upson, 1897-05, undated (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia
    - Memorial tribute from Wheaton College, 1935 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous memorabilia (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1)
    - "The Affair of William Strickland & Co." (manuscript) (Box 1)
    - Articles for Godey's Magazine and Christian Herald, 1893, 1909 (Box 1)
  - Poems (Box 1)
  - Notes (Box 2)
    - "My Reminiscences," undated (Box 2)
    - European travel journal, 1923-25 (Box 2)
    - Diaries (8), 1862-68, 1888 (Box 2)
    - History notebook, 1866 (Box 2)
    - White Butterfly by Kate Upson Clark, 1900 (Box 2)